


-------------INSTRUCTIONS_DELAY_DISCOUNTING--------------

1. OPEN THE TASK FOLDER
2. DOUBLE CLICK ON THE FILE NAMED "DelayDiscountingTitrated.ebs2."
3. YOU WILL BE PROMPTED TO ENTER THE SUBJECTS'S NUMBER. ENTER A NUMBER (NO LETTERS) AND CLICK "OK"
4. YOU WILL BE PROMPTED TO ENTER THE SUBJECT'S AGE. ENTER IT AND CLICK "OK."
5. READ THE TASK INSTRUCTIONS TO THE PARTICIPANT.
   EXPLAIN THAT OPTIONS WILL APPEAR ON THE SCREEN SIMULTANEOUSLY--AN OPTION TO HAVE SOME AMOUNT OF MONEY IMMEDIATELY, AND ANOTHER TO HAVE A DIFFERENT AMOUNT AT A DELAY.
   EMPHASIZE WHICH KEYS NEED TO BE PRESSED TO SELECT ONE OF THE TWO OPTIONS.
   ***EMPHASIZE THAT THIS IS A PREFERENCE TASK.THERE IS NO RIGHT OR WRONG ANSWER. PARTICIPANTS SHOULD BE ENCOURAGED TO SELECT CHOICES BASED ON THEIR PREFERENCE.***

THE TASK WILL TERMINATE ON ITS OWN ONCE ALL TRIALS HAVE BEEN COMPLETED.

THERE IS NO TIME LIMIT ON THIS TASK. 



Steinberg, L., Graham, S., O’Brien, L., Woolard, J., Cauffman, E. and Banich, M. (2009), Age Differences in Future Orientation and Delay Discounting. Child Development, 80: 28–44. doi: 10.1111/j.1467-8624.2008.01244.x

This research was supported by the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation Research Network on Adolescent Development and Juvenile Justice.



The delay discounting task was administered on a laptop computer (The task took about 10 min to complete.). In our adaptation of the task, the amount of the delayed reward was held constant at $1,000. We varied the time to delay in six blocks (1 day, 1 week, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, and 1 year), presented in a random order. For each block, the starting value of the immediate reward was $200, $500, or $800, randomly determined for each participant. The respondent was then asked to choose between an immediate reward of a given amount and a delayed reward of $1,000. If the immediate reward was preferred, the subsequent question presented an immediate reward midway between the prior one and the zero (i.e., a lower figure). If the delayed reward was preferred, the subsequent question presented an immediate reward midway between the prior one and the $1,000 (i.e., a higher figure). Participants then worked their way through a total of nine ascending and descending choices until their responses converged and their preference for the immediate and delayed reward are equal, at a value reflecting the “discounted” value of the delayed reward (i.e., the subjective value of the delayed reward if it were offered immediately; Green, Myerson, & Macaux, 2005), referred to as the “indifference point” (Ohmura et al., 2006). An individual with a relatively lower indifference point and/or a relatively higher (steeper) discount rate is relatively more oriented toward the immediate than the future. For each individual, we computed the indifference point for each delay interval, the average indifference point, and the discount rate. As in previous studies, delay discounting is correlated with intelligence: In the present sample, the correlation between IQ and individuals’ average indifference point is r= .31, p < .001, and the correlation between IQ and individuals’ discount rate is r=−.27, p < .001. The correlation between individuals’ average indifference point and their discount rate is, as expected, negative, r=−.41, p < .001, given that individuals with a higher discount rate are more likely to prefer smaller, immediate rewards. With IQ controlled, delay discounting performance is unrelated or only marginally related, r≈ .10 to performance on the measures of executive functioning included in the test battery.   